Guide to the John S. Bradway correspondence with Richard M. Nixon, 1959-1978 UA.29.02.268
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John S. Bradway correspondence with Richard M. Nixon
1959-1978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bradway, John S. (John Saeger), 1890-1985
UA.29.02.268
0.5 Linear Feet
John S. Bradway was a professor to Richard Nixon while he was a student at Duke Law School in the 1930s. The collection consists of letters, telegrams, and cards sent to and from Richard Nixon prior to his 1968 election, during his presidency and subsequent impeachment, and following his resignation in 1974 during his second term in office. Topics in the correspondence include the Vietnam War, political protests, Nixon's coverage in the press, his impeachment trial, and his book.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
John Saeger Bradway (1890-1985) taught law at Duke University School of Law from 1931 to 1959, where Nixon was one of his students. Bradway taught in California until his retirement in 1970. Bradway was married to Mary Henderson in 1921. He died on January 2, 1985 in Eureka, California.
Richard Milhous Nixon (1913-1994) attended the Duke University School of Law from 1934 to 1937, graduating number three in a class of twenty-six. During his three years at Duke, Nixon was active in the Duke Bar Association and was elected President in his senior year. Following school, Nixon began a political career. He was a Senator for California (1950-1953), the nation's 36th vice president (1953 to 1961), and was elected the 37th president of the United States, serving from 1969 until his resignation in 1974.
Nixon was the first U.S. president, since Andrew Johnson in 1868, to be the subject of formal impeachment proceedings in the House of Representatives. The impeachment process began on October 30, 1973, following a series of staff firings and resignations known as the Saturday Night Massacre prompted by the Nixon administration's attempt to cover-up its involvement with the 1972 break-in at the Democratic National Committee headquarters at the Watergate office complex in Washington, D.C.
On May 9, 1974, formal hearings in the impeachment inquiry of President Nixon began, culminating July 27–30, 1974, when the Democratic-led Judiciary Committee approved three articles of impeachment charging the president with obstruction of justice; injury to the constitutional rights of citizens; and the abuse of power. Once Nixon was told his that both his impeachment and his conviction were inevitable he resigned the presidency on August 9, 1974, before the House could vote on the articles of impeachment.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The John S. Bradway correspondence with Richard M. Nixon were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2020.
Related Materials
John S. Bradway papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Richard M. Nixon Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Richard Nixon Portrait Committee Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Nixon Library Controversy Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of carbon copies of letters Bradway sent to Nixon, and letters, telegrams, and cards from Richard Nixon prior to his 1968 election, during his presidency and subsequent impeachment, and following his resignation in 1974 during his second term in office. Topics in the correspondence include the Vietnam War, political protests, Nixon's coverage in the press, his impeachment trial, and his book. Also included is correspondence between Bradway and President Gerald Ford.
Presidents -- United States -- Correspondence; Politicians -- United States -- Correspondence; Impeachments; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1972; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1968; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Journalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Faculty; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Watergate Trial, Washington, D.C., 1973; Duke University. School of Law -- Faculty; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006; Nixon, Pat, 1912-1993; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Ford, Betty, 1918-2011
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1959 May 12 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Content discusses Bradway's upcoming retirement.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1959 May 18 (Box 1)
- Rita Leavitt to Richard Nixon, 1964 Jul 30 (Box 1)
  Bradway's secretary, Rita Leavitt, writes to tell Nixon that Bradway is out of town, and has not received his invitation to a meeting at the Annual Meeting of the American Bar Association. The invitation is included with the letter.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1964 Dec 16 (Box 1)
  Nixon asks for Bradway's opinion on conservatives and liberals as TV and radio commentators, and his views on the student protests at the University of California, Berkeley.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1964 Dec 22 (Box 1)
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1965 Mar 29 (Box 1)
  This letter includes a copy of The Choice in Vietnam which is a speech delivered by Nixon at a meeting of the 87th, 88th, and 89th clubs in New York.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1968 Nov 8 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to congratulate Nixon on his election as President of the United States.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1969 Jun 30 (Box 1)
  As President, Nixon writes to Bradway discussing his stay in the hospital, and his memories of Bradway as a professor at Duke.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1969 Jul 29 (Box 1)
  Bradway discusses that both he and Nixon received Quaker upbringings, and that he prays for him daily.
- Richard Nixon Oral History Project, 1969 Oct-Nov; 7 items (Box 1)
  Contents include correspondence between Harry Jeffrey and Bradway regarding interviewing Bradway for the Richard Nixon Oral History Project at California State College, Fullerton.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1970 Feb 3 (Box 1)
  Includes a signed, printed card which discusses appreciation for support of pursuit of peace in Vietnam.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1970 Apr 15 (Box 1)
  Bradway discusses his thoughts on a recommendation for the Supreme Court.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1972 Apr 19 (Box 1)
  Includes an invitation to dinner at the White House.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1972 Apr 29 (Box 1)
  Bradway declines an invitation to the White House and comments on the failure of the news media.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1972 May 10 (Box 1)
  Nixon recalls Bradway and faculty's kindness extended during his three years at Duke Law School, and states he will have Bradway's message to the Class of 1937 copied and sent to each member of the Class.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, circa 1972 Nov (Box 1)
  Content includes a printed telegram requesting Bradway's vote signed by Nixon and paid for by the Committee to Re-elect the President.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1972 Nov 29 (Box 1)
  Includes a signed, printed card which discusses appreciation for Bradway's message of congratulations. The card is also signed by Pat Nixon.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1973 Jan 27 (Box 1)
  Bradway suggests having Congress investigate the possible origins of funding for "Peace Demonstrations" of the Vietnam War.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1973 Aug 3 (Box 1)
  Bradway suggests Nixon explore hiring George W. Kraft, a former Duke student, to ensure he have an honest man work for him.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1973 Oct 18; 2 items (Box 1)
  Nixon wishes Bradway well during his upcoming surgery. Also included is a carbon copy of the letter to Ralph A. Newman.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1973 Nov 26; 2 items (Box 1)
  Includes signed, printed cards thanking Bradway for his support.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1973 Dec 6 (Box 1)
  Bradway comments on Senator Javits' speech, and the Republican Party's Watergate Affair mistakes.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1973 Dec 12 (Box 1)
  Includes a Christmas card from the White House.
- John Bradway to Gerald Ford, 1974 Jan 24 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Vice President Ford discussing the possibility of Congress, AFL-CIO, or the press as the pressure groups supporting Nixon's impeachment.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Jan 29 (Box 1)
  Bradway discusses the need for fairness in the impeachment coverage.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1974 Feb 6; 2 items (Box 1)
  Nixon writes to Bradway on the occasion of his eighty-fourth birthday. A photocopy of the original letter is also included.
- Ralph A. Newman to John Bradway, 1974 Feb 8-11; 3 items (Box 1)
  Newman corresponds with Bradway regarding his upcoming birthday, and communications with Nixon.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Feb 14 (Box 1)
  Bradway encourages Nixon to "Stay With It," as the Congressional impeachment investigation continues.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Feb 19, Feb 23; 2 items (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Nixon to thank him for his birthday greeting letter, and also states that "your resignation would be a major catastrophe," and stating he will frame and hang his letter.
- Jan Fuller to John Bradway, circa 1974 Mar (Box 1)
  Jan Fuller sends a clipping to Bradway regarding a missing Duke University Law School painting of Nixon found hidden in the ceiling of the building.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1974 Mar 19 (Box 1)
  Includes signed, printed cards thanking Bradway for his confidence and support.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Apr 30 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes regarding Nixon's television presentation, and discusses confidentiality and the press.
- White House to John Bradway, 1974 May 17 (Box 1)
  Includes appreciation for Bradway's message and a copy of an article by Dean Burch, "What Nixon Knew, and When, and What He Did: A View."
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 May 18; 2 items (Box 1)
  Bradway discusses his receipt of a letter from Senator Tower, and a copy of his response stating his disappointment with the Republican Party response to the impeachment.
- John Bradway to the American Bar Association, 1974 May 31 (Box 1)
  Bradway corresponds with Chesterfield Smith and Louis Potter of the American Bar Association (ABA) suggesting the ABA pursue a professional role in the upcoming impeachment trial.
- White House to John Bradway, 1974 Jun 17; 2 items (Box 1)
  Includes appreciation for Bradway's message of support, and copy of an article by Dean Burch, "What Nixon Knew, and When, and What He Did: A View."
- United States International University to John Bradway, 1974 Jul 26 (Box 1)
  Robert K. Castetter, Dean of the School of Law responds to a letter from Bradway stating they will send him a copy of remarks made by speakers during the program honoring Bradway.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Jul 26, Aug 7, Aug 9; 3 items (Box 1)
  Bradway writes letters of support and comments that Nixon "will go down in history as one of our finest Presidents," as Nixon officially resigns the presidency on August 8, 1974.
- John Bradway to Bob Michel, 1974 Aug 9 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes expressing his disappointment in the Republican Party and choosing not to send a contribution.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1974 Aug 22 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to "Richard" suggesting that he write books or articles on his side of Watergate Affair.
- John Bradway to Gerald Ford, 1974 Nov 14 (Box 1)
  Bradway has suggestions for the new president regarding the Watergate Affair and the United States Constitution involving the issues of high crimes and misdemeanors, the Supreme Court, and due process of the law.
- David Wilson to John Bradway, 1974 Nov 28 (Box 1)
  Wilson writes thanking Bradway for his support of the Republican party.
- John Bradway to David Wilson, 1974 Dec 1 (Box 1)
  Bradway has suggestions for Wilson including encouraging Nixon to write a book, and the issues of high crimes and misdemeanors, and the impeachment process.
- Robert Havel to John Bradway, 1974 Dec 2 (Box 1)
  The Director of Public Information thanks Bradway for his letter on behalf of President Johnson.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1975 Jul 2 (Box 1)
  Nixon writes to Bradway commenting on his project of writing about the Watergate Affair.
- John Bradway to the Law Alumni Journal, 1975 Apr 14 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to the editor to offer corrections to a reference to him in the journal.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1975 Jun 24 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes Nixon he is still thinking of the Watergate Affair, and that the Democrats' version seemed to be "a lot of shadow boxing but has little relation to the actual controversy."
- John Bradway to Rabbi Korff, 1976 Apr 21 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Korff with comments on his book The Personal Nixon.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1976 May 7 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Nixon that he read Rabbi Korff's book. Bradway also writes that press accounts of Nixon left him feeling that he was "witnessing a "lynching" party."
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1976 Jun1 (Box 1)
  Nixon writes that he is working his book.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1976 Aug 13 (Box 1)
  Nixon thanks Bradway for his concern over Pat's illness, and gives a health update.
- John Bradway to Gerald Ford, 1976 Nov 3 (Box 1)
  Bradway thanks Ford for supporting his former law student, Nixon, while he faced "what some people would regard as a lynching party."
- Gerald Ford to John Bradway, 1976 Nov 29 (Box 1)
  Ford thanks Bradway for his kind message.
- Gerald Ford to John Bradway, 1976 Dec 17; 2 items (Box 1)
  Ford writes to thank Bradway for his support of the Republican National Committee, and includes photographs of himself and Betty Ford.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1977 May 5 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Nixon with comments on his television interview with David Frost.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1977 May 20 (Box 1)
  Nixon thanks Bradway for his comments on the interview, and notes he will try to incorporate Bradway's analysis in his book.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1977 Jun 2 (Box 1)
  Nixon sends Bradway a copy of an article on the powers of the Presidency he as written for publication in The Washington Star.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1977 Jul 26 (Box 1)
  Nixon sends Bradway an autographed copy of his daughter Julie Nixon's book, "Special People."
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1977 Sep 19 (Box 1)
  Nixon thanks Bradway for his letter regarding the last of the Frost television interviews.
- John Bradway to Richard Nixon, 1978 Oct 15 (Box 1)
  Bradway writes to Nixon to thank him for the autographed copy of his book, and offers his comments. Only the first page of the letter is included.
- Richard Nixon to John Bradway, 1978 Oct 20 (Box 1)
  Nixon writes to Bradway thanking him for his comments on Memoirs, and mentioning memories of Mrs. Bradway forty years earlier.
- Grosset & Dunlap to John Bradway, circa 1978 (Box 1)
  Includes an advertising letter from Grosset & Dunlap, Inc., offering autographed Deluxe and Presentation Editions of Nixon's book, Memoirs.